Ciaran Carson papers, circa 1970-2010
Emory University
- Writings by Carson, circa 1970-2009, Series 2; Boxes 8-28, 48-59; OP1-5
  - Poetry, 1971-2009, Subseries 2.2; Boxes 12-18, 50-54; OP 1-2
    - Uncollected poetry, 1971-2007, Subseries 2.2b; Boxes 16-18, 54; OP2
      - "The Émigré," TS (Box 17, Folder 25)
      - "Fathers" and "Basáin Mhara," TS and notes (Box 54, Folder 13)
      - "Firing Range," TS (Box 17, Folder 26)
      - "First Times," TS [See also Subseries 2.2: The Lost Explorer, "Great-Grandmother"] (Box 17, Folder 27)
      - "Fishing for Eels," MS and TS, February 2007 (Box 54, Folder 14)
      - "Flatland," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.2: Belfast Confetti, "Hamlet"] (Box 17, Folder 28)
      - "For Reasons of Security," (Box 17, Folder 29)
      - "From Kilnaman to Kilmore," TS (Box 17, Folder 30)
      - "Gag," TS (Box 17, Folder 31)
      - "The gents' umbrellas are dark, funereal," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 32)
      - "Gerhardt Langenscheidt and Lotte Weimar," TS[originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 33)
      - "A Ghost Story," TS [variant titles: "Ghost", "Ghosts"] [See also Subseries 2.2: The Irish for No, TS, annotated by Tess Gallagher] (Box 17, Folder 34)
      - "Gifts," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 35)
      - "Gifts," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.1: Notebooks, Belfast Group Sheets 1971-1972] (Box 17, Folder 36)
      - "Gig Down the Line," TS (Box 17, Folder 37)
      - "The Gilt Lighthouses," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 38)
      - "The Glass Factory," TS (Box 17, Folder 39)
      - "Grandma," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 40)
      - "Great Northern Railway Terminus," TS (Box 17, Folder 41)
      - "Green Star, Gold Ring, Orange Lily," TS [originally filed by Carson in First Language notebook] (Box 17, Folder 42)
      - "Gun," TS (Box 17, Folder 43)
      - "Halliday's Road," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 44)
      - "Hearing a Knock," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from On the Night Watch] (Box 54, Folder 15)
      - "High Windows," MS and TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from For All We Know] (Box 54, Folder 16)
      - "The Holy Sepulchre," TS, 28 August 2006 (Box 54, Folder 17)
      - "How Good," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from On the Night Watch] (Box 54, Folder 18)
      - "How to Remember," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 45)
      - "I am not a guest," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 46)
      - "I slept here last night, hidden," TS (Box 17, Folder 47)
      - "Index," TS, 6 April 2006 (Box 54, Folder 19)
      - "Interface," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] (Box 54, Folder 20)
      - "The Irish Ordinance Survey," [See Subseries 2.2: Belfast Confett i, "Nub"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "It was a story that kept trying to be born," MS [filed by Carson with materials from The First Language] (Box 17, Folder 48)
      - "Last Post," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] [see also Subseries 2.2: Collected Poems, "The War Correspondent," TS] (Box 54, Folder 21)
      - "Lavender," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 49)
      - "The Love-Child," TS [originally found with series 5, Belfast Group worksheets, 1971-1972] (Box 17, Folder 50)
      - "The Lovers," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 51)
      - "The mantelpiece is heavy with objects," MS and TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 52)
      - "The Maze," TS [See Subseries 2.2: The Lost Explorer: "Smithfield," verso of MS] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "The Meadow," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 53)
      - "Measgra Cainte (a miscellany of talk)," TS (Box 17, Folder 54)
      - "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," TS [included with contract for readings at Down Civic Arts Centre, 9 February 2001] (Box 17, Folder 55)
      - "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," proofs [includes "Tru-Fit Exhausts," and TLS from Chicago Review editor, 5 August 1999] (Box 17, Folder 56)
      - "Milltown Cemetery," MS and TS [See also Subseries 2.2: Belfast Confetti, "Hamlet"] [MS found in Belfast Confetti notebook No. 2] (Box 17, Folder 57)
      - "Montezuma's Revenge," TS [early typescript found in Belfast Confetti notebook No. 2] (Box 17, Folder 58)
      - "Mountain Flax," TS [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 17, Folder 59)
      - "Moving," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 60)
      - "New Poems," TS (Box 54, Folder 22)
      - "News," MS [See Subseries 2.2: The New Estate and Other Poems, verso of "The Alhambra"] [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Night Out," TS [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems: "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," TS] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Nub," MS and TS [variant title: "Migraine"] (Box 17, Folder 61)
      - "Occupation," TS, 27-30 August 2006 (Box 54, Folder 23)
      - "Ode to a Nightingale," TS (Box 17, Folder 62)
      - "One Exchange Place," TS [See also Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "Tru-Fit Exhausts"] (Box 17, Folder 63)
      - "Onset," TS (Box 54, Folder 24)
      - "Palestine Street," MS and TS, 26 August 2006 [originally filed by Carson with materials from For All We Know] (Box 54, Folder 25)
      - "Paradise," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 64)
      - "Paul," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 65)
      - "Peace," TS, circa 2001 [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] (Box 54, Folder 26)
      - "Peace," TS and notes, 31 August-1 September 2006 [originally filed by Carson with materials from For All We Know] (Box 54, Folder 27)
      - "Perhaps a diary is an atlas" TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 66)
      - "Philomena," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 67)
      - "Play Shop" [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "Moving"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Post Mortem on a Mass Grave," TS [See Subseries 2.2: Series 5, Belfast Group Worksheets] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Power," TS [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "Wet Leaves"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Power Failure," TS [included with the Belfast Group Sheets 1971-1972] (Box 17, Folder 68)
      - "The quality of mercy is not strained," TS [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "Snow"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Quarter" and "Onset," offprint, 17 August 2006 (Box 54, Folder 28)
      - "Raftery," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 69)
      - "Redevelopment," TS [considered for inclusion in The Irish for No] (Box 17, Folder 70)
      - "The Reliquary," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 71)
      - "Remembering Peace," TS [originally included with The Alexandrine Plan materials] (Box 17, Folder 72)
      - "The Return," TS (Box 17, Folder 73)
      - "Revelation," TS, September 2006 [originally filed by Carson with materials from For All We Know] (Box 54, Folder 29)
      - "The Riddle of the Sands," TS [originally arranged with Opera Et Cetera] [February 2, 1994] [Published in Southern Review 31:3 (1995)] (Box 17, Folder 74)
      - "The Riddle of the Sands," proof for Southern Review, Summer 1995 (Box OP2, Folder -)
      - "Rot," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] [variant title: "Urban Rot"] (Box 54, Folder 30)
      - "Rye Whiskey," TS [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 17, Folder 75)
      - "Saw," TS (Box 17, Folder 76)
      - "Saying Prayers," TS [See Subseries 2.2: The New Estate, verso of "Soot"] [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "The Schoolmaster's Daughter," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 77)
      - "The Scribe in the Woods," TS (Box 54, Folder 31)
      - "2nd Movement," MS (Box 17, Folder 78)
      - "Second Take," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 79)
      - "Semi-Detached," MS and TS (Box 17, Folder 80)
      - "7," TS (Box 17, Folder 81)
      - "Shaftsbury Square," TS (Box 17, Folder 82)
      - "The Shed," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 17, Folder 83)
      - "The Silver Age," MS and TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 17, Folder 84)
      - "Small Beer," TS (Box 17, Folder 85)
      - "Snow," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - "Snowstorm," TS [variant title: "Quark"] (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - "Songs from the Life of Billy Pilgrim," TS [included with the Belfast Group Sheets 1971-1972] (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - "Song of the Wandering Tailor," TS [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - "St. Gall's Public Elementary School," TS (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - "Stone Hand," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - "A sudden musical ting," TS [originally filed by Carson in Belfast Confetti notebook No. 1] (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - "Summer of 1955," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 18, Folder 8)
      - "Summer Sadness," TS [originally included with The Alexandrine Plan materials] (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - "Susceptible to dreams, to vanities / What does the meadow do in winter" TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 10)
      - "Teaching," MS [See Subseries 2.2: The Insular Celts, "St. Ciaran's Island"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Tennyson Street," TS [considered for inclusion in Belfast Confetti] (Box 18, Folder 11)
      - "Territory," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] (Box 54, Folder 32)
      - "There," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 12)
      - "Three Sonnets," TS [sequence includes: "Obituary for Two Sisters" and "Heartbreak House,"] [originally found with Series 5, Belfast Group worksheets, 1971-1972] (Box 18, Folder 13)
      - "Thursday," TS [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - "To the German Language," TS (Box 18, Folder 15)
      - "Traffic," TS [circa 2000-2002] (Box 18, Folder 16)
      - "Trick or Treat," TS, 26 August 2006 [originally filed by Carson with materials from For All We Know] (Box 54, Folder 33)
      - "Tru-Fit Exhausts," TS with "One Exchange Place," TS [included with contract for readings at Down Civic Arts Centre, 9 February 2001] (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - "Tru-Fit Exhausts," proof [See Subseries 2.2: Uncollected Poems, "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," proofs] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Trust," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from Breaking News] (Box 54, Folder 34)
      - "Tunney," MS (Box 18, Folder 18)
      - "Upset bee buzzes," MS [haiku] (Box 18, Folder 19)
      - "Urlár: a Gloss" [originally filed by Carson with materials from On the Night Watch] (Box 54, Folder 35)
      - "The vanity case you lost," MS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 20)
      - "Vespers," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from On the Night Watch] (Box 54, Folder 36)
      - "A Visit to the Slate Mines," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 18, Folder 21)
      - "Waiting Room," TS [considered for inclusion in The Irish for No] (Box 18, Folder 22)
      - "The Waitress," MS [See Subseries 2.2: The Insular Celts, "St. Ciaran's Island"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Watching Bowls," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The Lost Explorer] (Box 18, Folder 23)
      - "Water and the Lady," TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 24)
      - "We did her injury, to think her death" MS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 25)
      - "Wednesday," TS [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 18, Folder 26)
      - "West Bank" [See Subseries 2.2: Belfast Confetti, "Hamlet"] (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Wet Leaves," MS [verso: "Power"] [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 27)
      - "When I am rich," TS [See also Subseries 2.2: The Insular Celts, "St. Ciaran's Island"] [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 28)
      - "When the man with the horse's head stepped out," TS [originally filed by Carson in Belfast Confetti notebook No. 3] (Box 18, Folder 29)
      - "When the shadow brought his law of enmity," TS [originally included with The Alexandrine Plan materials] (Box 18, Folder 30)
      - "'The Wild Colonial Boy': A Commentary," MS and TS [variant title: "Some Variations on 'The Wild Colonial Boy'"] [originally filed by Carson in First Language notebook] (Box 18, Folder 31)
      - "The Window," MS and TS [variant titles: "Looking at the Body," and "The marbled map of the sky"] [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 32)
      - "Wren Boys," TS [variant title: "Jinny the Mouse"] [included with The Twelfth of Never materials] (Box 18, Folder 33)
      - "Wrong Side of the Fence," TS [See also Subseries 2.2: The Irish for No, TS, annotated by Tess Gallagher] (Box 18, Folder 34)
      - "Your mouth, half-opened, breathed" TS [originally filed by Carson with materials from The New Estate] (Box 18, Folder 35)
      - Uncollected sequence of poems, MS, TS, and notes [contains "Raglan Street," "Berlin Street," "Crimea Street," "Miss Moran Tobacconist," "The Millfield Foundry Belfast," "One Exchange Place," and "Tru-Fit Exhausts] [originally filed by Carson with materials from "The War Correspondent" in Breaking News] (Box 54, Folder 37)
      - Uncollected sequence of poems, TS, July 1999 [contains "St. Gall's Public Elementary School," "The Belfast Hospital for Sick Children," "Mandelstam Street," "Addition Place," "Inkerman Street," "Raglan Street," "Concert at the Great Northern Railway Station," "Church of the Most Holy Redeemer," "Berlin Street," "Ambrose Serridge Bookseller," "The Dolphin Café," "Crimea Street," "Sevastopol Street," and "Jerusalem Street"] (Box 54, Folder 38)
      - Unidentified manuscript fragments (Box 18, Folder 36)
      - Unidentified notes (Box 54, Folder 39)
      - Unidentified typescript fragments (Box 18, Folder 37)
  - Translations, 1994-2008, Subseries 2.3; Boxes 18-20, 54-57
    This subseries contains Carson's translations of others' work from 1994-2007. Both poetry and prose are represented here. Stemming from the fact that Irish is Carson's first language, translation is an important feature of Carson's writing life and has become increasingly predominant in Carson’s writing since 1993. He has translated from Ovid's Latin as well as the Irish of various friends and colleagues. Also, Carson has done translations of contemporary Romanian, and he has worked extensively on nineteenth-century French Symbolist poets. In some cases, translations have been commissioned for other book projects, and when these pieces have also been included in volumes authored by Carson, a note refers to the relevant work in Subseries 2.2 or 2.4. Translations of Carson’s work can be found in Series 3: Writings by Others.
    - After Ovid (1994)
    - "Ascalaphus," corrected galley proof [See also Subseries 2.2: First Language, "Ovid: Metamorphoses, V, 529-550"] (Box 18, Folder 38)
    - "Aurora and Memnon," corrected galley proof [See also Subseries 2.2: First Language, "Ovid: Metamorphoses, XIII, 576-619"] (Box 18, Folder 39)
    - "Down Under," corrected galley proof [variant title: "Latitude 38 S"] [See also Subseries 2.2: First Language, "Latitude 38 S"] (Box 18, Folder 40)
    - "Hecuba," corrected galley proof with notes by Tess Gallagher [See also Subseries 2.2: First Language, "Ovid: Metamorphoses, XIII, 439-575"] (Box 18, Folder 41)
    - After Ovid Correspondence: 3 ALS from Michael Hoffman and James Lasdun to Carson (January - March 1993). (Box 18, Folder 42)
    - When the Tunnels Meet: Contemporary Romanian Poetry (1996), translations of Stefan Augustin Doinas
    - "Alibi," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 43)
    - "Bird," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 44)
    - "Cortege," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 45)
    - "Me and My Cousin," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 46)
    - "The News," MS (Box 18, Folder 47)
    - "A Pair," TS (Box 18, Folder 48)
    - "The Poet as Snow-Merchant," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 49)
    - "Siege," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 50)
    - "Snap," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 51)
    - "The Words," MS and TS (Box 18, Folder 52)
    - When the Tunnels Meet, TS biography of Doinas by Nicolae Balota (Box 18, Folder 53)
    - When the Tunnels Meet, ALS from John Fairleigh: January 17, 1993; July 28, 1995; September 6, 1995; plus translations of Carson by Doinas (Box 18, Folder 54)
    - When the Tunnels Meet, galley proofs of translations with ALS from Neil Astley (Box 18, Folder 55)
    - The Alexandrine Plan (1998)
    - Folder for drafts, with proposed title, "The Alexandrine Campaign / Plan" (Box 18, Folder 56)
    - Assorted French originals (Box 18, Folder 57)
    - "1870," TS (Box 18, Folder 58)
    - "Aphrodite's Ghost," TS (Box 18, Folder 59)
    - "At the Sign of the Swan," TS [variant titles: "The impending huge today of virgin snow", "Sculpted Ice"] (Box 18, Folder 60)
    - "Beauty," TS (Box 18, Folder 61)
    - "Blue Grass," TS (Box 18, Folder 62)
    - "Brief Encounter," TS [variant title: "She Passed Me By"] (Box 18, Folder 63)
    - "Cats," TS (Box 18, Folder 64)
    - "Coexistences," TS (Box 18, Folder 65)
    - "The Dongless Bell," MS and TS [variant title: "The Flawed Bell"] (Box 18, Folder 66)
    - "The Enemy," TS (Box 18, Folder 67)
    - "The Green Bar," TS (Box 18, Folder 68)
    - "I Had a Life," TS [variant title: "A Former Life"] (Box 18, Folder 69)
    - "Just Crazy About You," TS (Box 18, Folder 70)
    - "The Lid," TS [See also Subseries 2.2: "The Dongless Bell" in The Alexandrine Plan] (Box 18, Folder 71)
    - "The Maid of Brobdingnag," TS (Box 18, Folder 72)
    - "Miss Malinger," TS [variant title: "Miss Cutie Pie"] (Box 18, Folder 73)
    - "O Happy Death," TS [variant title: "Dead Happy"] (Box 18, Folder 74)
    - "On the Road," TS (Box 18, Folder 75)
    - "Poster Advertising the Amazing Victory at Sarrebrük," TS (Box 18, Folder 76)
    - "Rainy Liaisons," TS (Box 18, Folder 77)
    - "Recalling the Belgian Friends," TS [variant title: "Remembering Belgian Friends"] (Box 18, Folder 78)
    - "The Riddle of the Pyx," TS [variant title: "Madame l'Angoisse, offing on high her onyx"] (Box 18, Folder 79)
    - "Sick," TS [variant title: "Bad", "Evil"] (Box 18, Folder 80)
    - "The Sleeper in the Valley," TS (Box 18, Folder 81)
    - "The Sonneteer," TS [variant title: "The Lonely Campanologist"] (Box 18, Folder 82)
    - "Stations," TS [variant title: "Sonnet"] (Box 18, Folder 83)
    - "Talk to Me," TS [variant title: "Bedtime Story"] (Box 18, Folder 84)
    - "To You," TS (Box 18, Folder 85)
    - "The Tomb of Charles Baudelaire," TS (Box 18, Folder 86)
    - "The Tomb of Edgar; Poe," TS (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - "The Tomb of Paul Verlaine," TS [variant title: "Tomb"] (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - "Travellers," TS (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - "Warriors," TS [variant title: "Duel"] (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - "The Whatnot," TS [variant title: "The Sideboard"] (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - The Alexandrine Plan, corrected typescript with photocopies of French poems (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - The Alexandrine Plan, corrected typescript with TLS and commentaries by Peter Fallon, 24 October 1997 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - The Alexandrine Plan, corrected typescript [photocopy] (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - The Alexandrine Plan, corrected proofs (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri (2002)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, assorted research materials (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, assorted MS notes (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, English cribs (photocopies) (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto I" (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto II" (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto III" (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto IV" (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto V" (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto VII" (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto VIII" (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto IX" (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XII" (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XIII" (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XIV" (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XV" (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XVI" (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XVII" (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XVIII" (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXI" (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXVI" (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXVII" (Box 19, Folder 30)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXIX" (Box 19, Folder 31)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXX" (Box 19, Folder 32)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "Canto XXXIII" (Box 19, Folder 33)
    - "Dante Among the Giants: A Translation of the Inferno, Canto XXXI," proof and published poem from TLS 29 September 2000 [See Series 4.1: Printed material by Carson] (Box -, Folder -)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "first fair copy" (Box 19, Folder 34)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "second fair copy" (3 August 2001) (Box 19, Folder 35)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS "final version" (October 2001) (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, copy-editor queries and Carson's responses, 14, 18 November 2001 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, "Acknowledgements," TS with TLS from Carson, 19 November 2001 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, galley proof (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, galley proof (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, proofs with TLS from Granta editor, 14 January 2002 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, "Introduction," TS with TLS from Carson to Editor, 24 January 2002 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, TS fragment (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - The Inferno of Dante Alighieri, cover art (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - The Midnight Court (2005)
    - Glossary, 24 November 2004 (Box 54, Folder 40)
    - The Midnight Court, TS, 23 November-29 December 2004 (Box 54, Folder 41)
    - The Midnight Court [stage version condensed for Galway youth theatre] TS, with handwritten notes, 23 November-29 December 2004 (Box 54, Folder 42)
    - The Midnight Court, TS, 29-30 December 2004 (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - The Midnight Court, TS, "Final," 3 January 2005 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - The Midnight Court, proofs, 4 March 2005 (Box 55, Folder 3)